You send a stablecoin over a blockchain and, you know, you could see when it was sent,
you could see when it was confirmed, you could see when it was delivered, you could see that it's
not just very basic things that why, you know, in addition to costs and, you know, things that
are more complicated that made us believe that this was a better, that money would be tokenized.
At some point in time, people, businesses, fintechs, banks would see the value in using this
emergent payment bill, and we were building for that future.
Welcome to Bankless, where we explore the frontier of internet money and internet finance.
This is Ryan Sean Adams, it's just me today, David Zhao, so I'm here to help you become
more Bankless. Every company in fintech is about to go through what I'm calling a crypto
transformation. Stripe is one of those companies. It's a $90 billion private payments company
behemoth, a company that does 1.3 of global GDP's worth of payments volume every single year.
They're definitely at the frontier of this crypto transformation. They're moving quite
quickly. They've invested big in stablecoins, and I think after the genius bill has just been signed,
they are doubling down in a big way. Zach Abrams is leading part of that transformation at Stripe.
Stripe just bought his stablecoin company, a company called Bridge for for $1 billion about
a year ago, and they've made more crypto acquisition since companies like Privy have been among them.
This conversation with Zach is a glimpse into how big fintech companies think about this transformation,
how they're going to evolve in the future. And it's a different perspective than the crypto
native one that we typically have on Bankless. That's why it's so valuable for us to hear.
It's also the story of Zach, who's this tenacious entrepreneur who had this thesis around stablecoins,
and persevered with that thesis, built this company through some very dark times,
leading to this major acquisition. Now, shortly after recording this episode,
Stripe launched some details on a layer one that they're sponsoring. People are calling this the
Stripe layer one. Their guest says it's more of a consortium. It's called Tempo. It's an EVM chain.
It's being launched with the consortium of fintech players. We discussed that too,
and why they didn't go with a layer one or a layer two. Big questions. What's Stripe doing next in
crypto? What's every fintech about to do? Zach Abrams helps answer those questions today.
So let's get right to that episode. But before we do, I want to thank the sponsors that made it
possible. Imagine a world where traditional finance meets the power of blockchain seamlessly.
That's what mantle is pioneering with blockchain for banking, a revolutionary new category at the
intersection of tradfi and web3. At the heart is you are the world's first money app built fully on
chain. It gives you a Swiss I ban account blending fiat currencies like the euro, the Swiss franc,
the United States dollar or the remimbi with crypto all in one place. Enjoy real world usability
and blockchains trust and programmability. Transactions post directly to the blockchain
compatible with tradfi rails and packed with integrated DeFi futures. You are transforms
mantle network into the ultimate platform for on-chain financial services. Unifying payments,
trading and assets like the MI4, the ME protocol and functions FBTC backed by developer grants,
ecosystem incentives and top distribution through the UR app, reward stations and buy bit launch pool.
For MNT holders, every economic activity in UR drives value back to you, embodying the entire
stack and future growth of this super app ecosystem. Follow mantle on X at mantle_official for the
latest updates on blockchain for banking. That's x.com/mantle_official. DGN started as a tight-knit
community on Farcaster and organically grew into one of the top meme coins on base. What began
as a simple idea, tip anyone who joins the fun, sparked an economy that turned into a movement.
The community runs the show from the logo and the lower to funding and building ambitious ideas
together. Over 1 million dee-gens now power each other with their generosity, creativity and ability
to get things done. At the center is the DGN token. It rewards engagement, fuels tipping and drives
the marketplace for builders and fans. That same energy gave rise to DGN chain, a fast low cost
layer three for new projects. And now the DGN app, the easiest way to connect, earn and participate
in decentralized social media with a built-in wallet and real token utility. In DGN, the hat stays on.
Join DGN and get on the app wait list at www.degen.tips.
Bankless Nation, very excited to introduce you to Zach Abrams. First, Zach, it's great to have
you on Bankless. And I gotta say this, the outset, congrats on selling your company, the company you
co-founded Bridge to Stripe. You did that in October of last year, at least that's what it was announced.
This was reportedly, I don't know if you can confirm this rumor, over a billion dollar acquisition.
Stripe's largest yet. So this was like a crypto unicorn and it's a big deal. Congrats on that.
Yeah, really, really appreciate it. And a lot has changed since then. That feels like 100 years
ago. Yeah, I don't know. It's kind of funny to me that Stripe bought a company pre-genius bill.
You know what I mean? Like bought a stablecoin company pre-genius bill. What kind of foresight
was that? I mean, it was pre the election when a bunch of stuff started to shift right after
pre-genius, a bunch of things. But I think the main thing probably for them and for us was that
you could start to see that it was working. And it had changed pretty quickly. Like two years
ago or three years ago, it was not working terribly well. Same coins or crypto in general.
Yeah, like the business, stablecoins generally, I mean, there was like Terra Luna and FTX and so on.
Forgot about that. Yeah, that's like in the in the long distant past now. But but it was like
starting to work. Like there were like real payments, companies and fintechs that were building on
us and you could squint and kind of see into the future that this was going to be very meaningful.
Yeah, it was very cool. I guess that's what the that's the genius of the calls and brothers.
They tend to build a squint and see you in the future. And they saw this one coming. I want to
talk about them in a minute, but first your own story, okay? Give us your, I guess, crypto
founder arc, if you will. And you could begin this wherever you want. I'll leave that open end
to see you. Where does the story begin for you? And how did you get on the other side? Now you're
working at Stripe Posta, maybe a billion dollar acquisition? Well, I guess for me, it kind of
started where most crypto founders start with auto parts. So coming out of college, I wanted to
be an operating partner at a private equity firm, which is a very bizarre thing to want to be.
Okay. And I went into private because like I thought it would be fun to like turn around and
like Rodney's companies. And we I joined this private equity firm that was buying distressed
businesses in 2009. The auto industry was like in, you know, complete turmoil. We bought an auto
parts company. I was like sent in as like a 22 year old to like be the CFO of this auto parts
company. Oh my god. How did you get that big as a 22 year old? Yeah, I mean, it was it was very
bleak though, because I was like, you know, you could imagine a 22 year old like, you know,
do we be kid? I was like going to Canada and like announcing to all of this company's, you know,
factory folks that we were closing factories in Canada, and then going to Mexico and cutting ribbons.
And I was like, this is not what I want to do. I want to like build stuff. This is the exact
opposite. And so I left private equity. And I had heard that people on the west coast were like
starting companies. But I went to Duke at the time. There were there were like legitimately,
when I graduated, maybe seven or eight computer science graduates, I do and all of Duke.
What was everyone doing over there? Everyone was doing a call on everyone going into like
going into going into investment banking and so on. And so I didn't really know people
that were starting companies. And so I decided I was like, I'm just going to start a company.
Like, I think that I can do it. And the first company we I wanted to start was actually like
a by now pay later, like, like, Klarna or a firm, but in 2010. And it's like the hardest business
imaginable to build because you have like large partnerships and you have like credit, you know,
and fraud and risk and, you know, all this, all this stuff. And I went to go raise money and I
went to the start this company. I thought the way that you did it is like you put together
presentation, you went to a VC, they gave you money. And then you hired an engineering team to
build with it. And so I was like sorely disappointed when I went into all these VCs offices. And then
they were like, show me the product. Like, you're not an engineer by training then you didn't study
it. Do I do? Okay, I didn't, I didn't study in a minute. And I didn't know anything. I didn't
even know what an engineer did. I didn't know what a designer did. I didn't know what a product
manager did. I was like the least equipped person to start a company imaginable. And then I went on
this like horrific one year journey to start this company where I like, you know, realized I need
to teach myself to code. So I went to like coding schools in New York. And then I realized I needed
co-founder and it was like co-founder dating, you know, it was like you go to a bar and it was like,
you know, 100 people like me and one engineer.
One very, very popular engineer. Exactly. Exactly. And eventually I met Sean, who is now my co-founder
for, for, for bridge, but Sean also had gone to Duke and, and I met Sean and this was maybe like
nine months into that journey. And I convinced him to start this company with me. And then we were
able to like raise money and build some momentum. And you know, then I moved to the west coast and,
and that company didn't end up working out. We sold it to, we sold it to square. But that's how I
kind of like ended up on this path and, you know, which started in a, in a wildly different place.
So that said you on the FinTech path, though. So I guess the square acquisition, maybe that
wasn't a, you know, like a banger, but at least it was sort of an exit out of the, the startup
pain that you were in. But you've since, in addition to square, you had some tenure at, at
Brex as well. And also Coinbase. So it's like FinTech plus, plus crypto is, is on the CD. Yeah, totally. I mean,
I did not. So each time it came to like find a new company. I found myself, you know, only in hindsight,
did I realize that I'm just like really interested in FinTech. It was just, you know, I was given a
menu of options and theory of like companies that I could go to. And every single time I happened to
pick the same type of item on the menu, which was the FinTech company. And in 2016, I think is when
I applied to Coinbase, I had this like real excitement around crypto. I had when when I had first moved
to San Francisco to start evenly, that was our first company. That's when Bitcoin ran out to like
$1,000, you know, $1,000 and then kind of crashed. That was maybe like 2012 or 2013 or something. And
so that's when both Sean and I had like, I think, I think it was true for Sean too. But we had bought
our first Bitcoin and, and like went to like meetups. And you know, people had like, you know, we're
building all, you know, all this Bitcoin mining stuff. And there was like all these hardware
companies and so on. Anyways, that had like kind of created an interest for me. And then
in 2016, I had this, you know, I was this is post square, this like just general excitement that I
thought that like this was going to be, I don't know what triggered it in me, but I thought this
was going to be really meaningful. And at the time I joined Coinbase and it was, you know, maybe
70 people or 60 people, but Coinbase is like a weird company. It's not like a company that exists
today where, you know, people have like 70 employees after like three months. Coinbase had like been
around for like five years or something. Like I was like employee number like 200 or something.
But at the time there were only 70 people there because it's just Coinbase had been through
so many different, you know, pivots and iterations and, and so on. And at the time when I joined
Coinbase had this is a kind of like an intersection with Stripe. Coinbase had just realized that paying
and buying stuff with Bitcoin on the internet was like not going to be the next thing. And like the
big marquee customers at the time were Stripe were was using it and overstock.com was using Stripe
was using Coinbase back then. Yeah, was using Coinbase back then for the the buy with Bitcoin
functionality. Okay. Okay. And right around the time that I joined was when, you know, we at
Coinbase realized, Oh, maybe that's not the thing. Maybe, you know, this exchange, you know, buying
and selling on the exchanges like has real legs and going to be going to be a big business. And then
2017 happened and it was like the wildest ride one could imagine. As Coinbase went from this like
very niche company to a major American, you know, financial services company almost overnight. And
then through that journey, one of the last things I worked on at Coinbase was USDC. And the launch
of USDC for the a lot of other people worked on the actual implementation of USDC. But I was
running the Coinbase consumer business. And our goal was to take USDC and figure out how to use it
and make it useful. And that's when as we started like figuring out how we would productize it,
came to this view that it could be this like first, you know, global store of value.
And there was a bunch of things around like turning Coinbase consumer into a new
bank that we wanted to do. But I never actually implemented and then left and then went to Brexit.
You went to Brexit. So you went back to the fintech side of things before then then starting a bridge.
Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. And it helped to have like two years away to kind of reflect on it and see a
lot of the problems that Brexit is because Brexit was like trying to expand internationally. And it
was like very clear as I had worked on a bunch of these different products, how, you know, a lot of
the domestic problems, especially in some of the more developed markets had been solved. But a lot
of the international problems had not been at all. What's so fascinating about your, I guess, resume
your experience here, Zach, and eventually like founding bridge is you're one of the few people who
are, I guess, a bridge between fintech and crypto, which is somewhat interesting. So my
experience is I found many of the fintech people skeptical about crypto. And many of the crypto
people just don't get fintech and don't even think it's irrelevant. And so the two kind of camps
have been growing independently for a while. It was crypto over here. And then fintech was doing
its own thing over here. I think that has changed this cycle, maybe starting in 23. But now it's
definitely crescendoed in 2025, where we're starting to see a convergence between fintech and crypto.
And in general, all of finance and cryptocurrency, are they different? Are they one and the same?
I think that's going to be a major theme of this episode, that convergence. It's certainly a theme
of this cycle. How did you, I guess, bridge that gap? What did you see that made you still not
skeptical enough about crypto? You're in fintech, but you're still open to crypto, right? And then
also in fintech, but not kind of like you bounce back and forth and you saw both of these worlds.
What did you see that the other fintech people didn't? I mean, first, I just
completely agree with the premise of the question. I think that one of the big,
one of the unique advantages that we had when we started bridge is that we sat in the middle,
we had a deep understanding of the financial landscape and an appreciation for what crypto
made possible. And there were just, there's like so few. I mean, now there are more. But at the time,
I felt like, and maybe this is true, but we were one of the only teams that sort of sat at this
at this intersection, you either were sort of like a religiously believed in crypto and felt that
like the existing financial ecosystem was like completely dysfunctional and would be replaced.
Or you lived in the existing financial system and thought that crypto was like purely speculative
and like, you know, crazy to scams and drug deals and crazy jpegs and just like all speculation,
nothing there, right? Yeah, exactly. And, and you know, the, the, the, the overlap of these two,
these two circles was incredibly, incredibly small, which created our opportunity.
It made it really hard at the beginning because like, you know, we, because of where we sat,
we had to go and work with banks. We, we were trying to sell to non crypto companies.
And so it was really challenging at the, at the beginning. I mean, because, because there was
nobody else who was at this, at this intersection, even today, it's, it's definitely a little bit
harder, but, but it's getting much, much easier. Like you found you founded bridge in 2022, right?
And the, that was a, that was a dark year for crypto. And so it was 2023, right? I mean,
that was just all of the momentum that we had. And I would say public goodwill that crypto had
as an industry came crashing down with sandbank been freed and FTX, the corresponding selloff and
all of the political goodwill to make something like stable coins happen in the US. That completely
evaporated. And of course, bankless listeners know we got years of operation choke point and like,
lots of bad things on the back of that. And here, you were trying to found a, like a bridge between
traditional finance, basically, FinTech and crypto during this, this very dark period of time. I mean,
what was that like? It was just as bad as you're describing and probably even worse because,
you know, Terrell Luna also happened, which really, you know, Terrell Luna kind of made stable coins
seem, seem, you know, tainted the entirety of the stable coin space. You know, you, you,
you also had a bunch of banks that were like crypto friendly banks that, that ended up like
going bankrupt. So all of the folks were in that Venn diagram. A lot of the folks got punished for
being in the middle of those two. So you had like signature and Silvergate went out of business.
You even had that was like 2023, right? It's a win. Yeah. Yeah. That was early 2023. And like,
you had BankProve, which most people don't talk about, but BankProve was another one of the,
one of the crypto friendly banks. They did a bunch of loans to Bitcoin miners.
And those loans went like massively underwater and the CEO got fired. I mean, it was like,
almost everybody who sat in this like intersection was, was punished in some capacity. The thing for
us is, I think when people start companies, there is like, like right now everybody wants to start
an AI company because it's like, you know, the invoke thing to do. And it's easy to start something
when everyone else externally is giving you validation that your thing is like an it thing
to do. But at the end of the day, making a company success was almost always like driven by a like
founder or the early teams, like just core belief that this thing needs to be built into existence.
And so the nice thing about founding the company when we did is that like that, that, that, you
know, desire to will this thing into existence was tested extremely early. And we just had a like
very core belief that stablecoins were represented a better means of building financial products.
And and not for some, you know, ideological reason, but because they literally made it like faster
and cheaper and more accessible and so on. And a better way of moving money for the same reasons,
it was tangibly cheaper and faster and a better mechanism to send funds like a great example that
that people, you know, I don't think a lot of people think about is like, if you send money
through the existing, you know, through ach or wire, you have no confirmation that your money
was ever delivered. Like, you just have no idea, you just send it and you just hope that it arrives.
Is that have you ever lost a wire that way?
So this was actually relatively recently, I sent a wire from one place to another is where,
yeah, I do some trad fi, I do have a bank, I'm not completely bankless everybody. So, you know,
full disclosure there and breaking wire breaking. Yeah, breaking the speaking of breaking,
the wire didn't end up, you know, you have to wait. And so I waited like 24 hours, 48 hours,
the wire did not end up where I had thought that I sent it. And I freaked out. And then I went
through this process of trying to figure out, like, did the wire actually settle? Like, where is it?
Where's the idea on Fedwire? And I must have talked to five or six people. This was between
a brokerage account I have and, you know, somewhere else in order. And they gave it to a wire tracing
team. They said, you know, the process would be like 48 hours to 72 hours turnaround time. I said,
how often do these cases get resolved? They say most of the time, but no promises. I was like,
you can't even track the wire? Like, this is crazy. Yeah. I mean, it's, it's nuts. And like,
you know, you send a stablecoin over, over a blockchain and, you know, you could see when it
was set, you could see when it was confirmed, you could see when it was delivered, you could see
that it's stuck. And, and it's like, like, just very basic things that why, you know, in addition to
costs and, you know, more things that are more complicated that, that, that made us believe that
this was a better, that money would be tokenized. And at some point in time, you know, people would
see the, you know, people, businesses, fintechs, banks would see the value and using this
emergent payment rail. And we were building for that future. We just had this very core
belief. And, and like, I had just seen it, this is one of the things that probably helped the
most of having this, like, history and fintech, I just seen this over and over again, that like,
fintech products that were successful, were successful for super obvious reasons. Like,
this isn't like a consumer company or something of like, why isn't why did Instagram beat whoever?
Why did Facebook beat, you know, this thing? You know, it's like, why did Robinhood win?
They had free trading, like, you know, when everyone else costs $5, it's like, you don't need to be
a genius to figure out why did Square win? Well, because it costs like, thousands of dollars a year
in 5% for a small business to process credit card transactions before they made it, you could
sign up instantly and they made it really cheap. Same thing for for for Stripe and so on. And with
financial products, eventually, over some arc of time, people are rational. So there was this perceived
stigma and perceived risk of building and using stablecoins, but there were all these very tangible
benefits of building and using stablecoins. And we were sort of building towards the future where
those perceivers would come down and people would realize the tangible, be able to realize
the tangible benefits. And for us, it started with those who were, you know, the most, the farthest
on the risk curve, you know, like startups and, and so on. And then now, as we've had, like,
regulatory clarity and so on, you know, folks who are not as far down the risk curve, you know,
and increasingly large enterprises and governments are now using stablecoins, which is really cool
to see. But it all emanated from that core belief that this like made financial sense for people
to build with. Yeah, that core belief, that was the unshakable thesis, I guess, back in 2022,
when it was not obvious, when it was not popular, Terra Luna collapsed, stablecoins are dead. This
will never work in crypto. Then you also had things like tether, which is like, what is that? It's
just like, AML, KYC, like, what's going on there? Is that, you know, shady sort of cryptocurrency,
what's going on? So that's the unshakable, like, you're the closest thing, I would say,
Zach, to like a stablecoin maxi that I've seen. We have all sorts of different religions in
crypto, as you know, and like, you might be the state, because I've heard you say things that
even you, you, you've been skeptical of some of the value proposition of crypto until stablecoins.
You said that stablecoins are the next evolution of money. I think this is also one of your quotes.
I'm building in crypto because I love financial services, and I believe this new platform can be
used to create better products. I'm not trying to free the world from centralization or build a
libertarian utopia. Some crypto native bank listeners might say, "Oh, okay, come on, Zach,
like, that's what we're trying to do in crypto." But you're pretty, like, you're pretty straightforward
in the fact that you think the big value proposition, the thing that you really want to
build in crypto, is this better fintech system based around stablecoins. So for people who aren't
aware, when they think stablecoins in crypto, they think maybe circle, they think maybe
tether some of the issuers, but you built something else. Although I believe Bridge does have a stablecoin
itself, but Bridge is kind of a stablecoin's payment platform. So what did you build over there
from 2022 up until you're acquired? What mission are you continuing with Bridge?
One of the other benefits of having worked at a bunch of these companies, like Work at Square,
Work at Brex or Work at, and now, Work at Stripe, is I've just seen how... I've always had this
interest in finance. Money is incredibly important in people's lives, obviously, and even very
marginal improvements to the way that people are able to accept or manage or facilitate the
movement of money. I've very tangibly seen the disproportionate impact that that has on people's
lives. Like, Take Square, for instance, you created a dongle, so it made it easier for someone to
accept a credit card payment. And at the time, a lot of people walked around and carried cash,
and what have you, but Square has enabled success of millions of merchants, enabled them to sell more
goods, enabled them their business to go from unprofitable to profitable, enabled them to capture
that incremental sale. And it's totally changed the livelihoods of many people. Stablecoins are
like that, but the scale is so much bigger. A stablecoin can be used and stored by people
all around the world. Now, with the stablecoin, people in every country have real economic choice
that they didn't have before. Now, with the stablecoin, you can move money between countries
that are fraction of the cost that you used to. And the opportunities that this opens up,
the applications that people are going to be able to build are pretty profound.
So we were always like very, you know, and I was in particular very motivated by this, like,
you know, long term, you know, belief in outcome and what could be possible. But yeah,
some of those things happen, you know, the only thing that was like that did, you know,
I'm not going to say that we were like completely unshakable. We always had this belief, but
the one thing that at some point, this was like, like, you know, the week that we launched our
APIs was the week that SBB collapsed. And I remember that that I had a conversation with Sean,
and I was like, you know, I still believe that we're right. But this might be now like 10 years away.
Like I thought the timelines might be off. Like little did you know, at that point in time,
you were just 24 months away from the first major crypto legislation to pass in the U.S.
and it happened to be stablecoin legislation. And that is going to lead to basically it's just
overnight legitimacy for stablecoins and a stablecoin bonanza explosion. And you were only 24 months
away from that at one of your lowest points as a startup founder thinking about your thesis.
It's incredible. Yeah. I mean, I think of anything like going through that at the beginning made us
like, you know, we were always extremely worried about like putting our like proverbial next meal
on the table, if you will, like because the first like 18 months of the company was literally just
like signing a bank partner and kicking us off signing a bank partner and going out of business,
signing a customer, then going out of business. And so it was like, even when things eventually
started to go right, we were like, wait a second, this is not going to last.
When did they start going right? Was that closer to 2024? They started going right.
I would say around June of 2023. Okay. Okay. June of 2023 is like, like we started early 2022.
So like 18 months in, they started going right. And so we had launched the API.
Maybe you come back to your previous question. What is Bridge? Bridge facilitates money movement
with stablecoins. Our view is that, you know, you have this fiat ecosystem that exists today and
stablecoins are like a scaling layer on top of the fiat ecosystem. And so you could kind of think of
our mental model is that stablecoins are like a layer two to the fiat systems layer one. And money
would need to move up into this tokenized form to take advantage of all these benefits. But it
will constantly need to settle back down to the layer one. And like a good example of this is a
cross border payment. Maybe it comes from fiat because, you know, the business or what have you
were are moving money in fiat and moves up to the scaling layer becomes tokenized,
it moves cross border and then it might settle back down into the recipient's bank account in fiat.
Okay. And so the the layer one in this example, the kind of the fiat layer, what is that? Is that
is that bank settlement that eventually gets down all the way to kind of like Fedwire somewhere?
Exactly. Exactly. And today, a lot of that money movement is up, you know, to the layer two and
then back down to the layer one. And and that's the way a lot of these and a great example of this is
Bridge facilitates people to store money and dollars all over the world. And they're storing
those money in stablecoin dollars. And a lot of the way that that plans in their account is maybe
they're a we work with scale AI. Scale AI is doing data labeling for AI models. Scales business
operates in US dollars in fiat US dollars. Scale sends that money to bridge bridge converts all
that money into stablecoins and then disperses the stablecoins to the data labelers all over the world.
And so it starts in the fiat layer, we can we tokenize all this money and then we disperse it
out to people to take advantage of the benefits that exists with stablecoins.
So is that what bridge essentially is? It's kind of a bridge between the fiat layer,
the layer one and all of these these banks that settle down to kind of the traditional bank system
in Fedwire and stablecoins, which is kind of the layer two and the tokenized world of stablecoins
that we know you guys sit in between those. And so when you were talking about APIs,
it's APIs between that banking layer and basically, you know, tokenized stablecoins.
Yep, exactly. And we basically built four developers. So those developers today are mostly
fintechs or banks or startups. And they want to take advantage of, you know, moving money,
cross border with stablecoins or accepting stablecoin payloads or giving their customers
the ability to store tokenized dollars or issuing cards on top of the stablecoins.
And we make all of those accessible through pretty simple APIs. So they don't have to learn all
the nuances of the crypto ecosystem and the fiat ecosystem and KYC and compliance and all those
things. It's just packaged up and then you can deliver whatever value it is you want to deliver
to your end customers. And so do you guys have a stablecoin like a USDC? We do. We do. Yep. We have
it. We have a stablecoin and, you know, we basically offer, you know, today, so we started off
back in coming back to your other question in June of when things started working.
Our first core product was our orchestration. We called our orchestration APIs and the
orchestration APIs just facilitate money movement between the fiat layer and the stablecoin layer.
And the first use case that started working was stablecoins for cross border payments.
And so when it really started working was this company Zulu, they were like our first like,
I would say like real customer, you know, like, like we, I tweeted something. They found us.
They were a huge pain in the butt to negotiate with. They like ground us down on fees, you know,
I almost gave up on the deal like a hundred times because I had never sold anything in my life.
And but then they came on the platform and they were taking Colombian pesos and converting them
into stablecoins and they needed someone like bridge to take those stablecoins and then convert
them into US dollars in the US so they could facilitate Colombian pesos to US dollar cross border
money movement. And so they just wanted a very simple service where they could send a stablecoin
and then tell us to deposit a stablecoin into a bank account. And so we created a product that
basically gives a bank account a crypto address. Wow. And so you just send a stablecoin to a
specific Ethereum or Solana or whatever address. And that address is programmed to always take it
convert it into a currency and send it via ACH or wire to the associated bank account. And very
simple product for them to use they would hit the API create it and send all they wanted to that
account and we would deposit it into into the account. And Zulu signed up. They were growing,
you know, 50 to 100% every month. And so as a result, bridge was growing 50 to 100%.
And and basically, you know, startups are this like really funny thing where in one lens,
you could look at our company and you could say, wow, this thing is super fragile and there's no
product market fit because it has one customer. We had others, but like really it was a one customer.
But on the other hand, you could look at it and you could say, wow, this is like really working
because it's growing, you know, 50 to 100% every single month. And they carried us for like the
first three, four months. And so I often wonder like, what it would have been like if we hadn't
have found them like the difference between like, you know, now you look at bridge and it's like,
oh, bridge is successful. And like, you know, we're part stripe and, you know, stablecoins are a
thing. And so it was like always going to work. But at that moment in time, the difference between
us being, you know, successful and like feeling like we had built something useful versus like
launching a product and having zero traction, you know, like literally zero traction, no customers,
no feedback was like one, one customer. It's incredible. And they gave us the confidence to
then go sell the pit. So they then go sell the US government. The US government was our next
big customers shockingly. Wait, what? What? Yeah, the US government.
So that the there was a government aid program where they were dispersing aid to frontline workers
across Lattam and all of this aid disbursement happened in stablecoins. And it happened previously
through Silvergate. And so then when Silvergate went out of business, they had no means of disbursement
payments, because it's really complicated. You would have to take the money from the government,
convert it into stablecoins, and then send thousands of stablecoin payments out. So like,
it was more than a human could do. You know, I was basically, so I was kind of thinking,
when you go through this story, I was kind of thinking about, do you remember our STEMI checks?
Do you remember the stimulus checks? Every American received and how weird and janky that was. I mean,
I think I got mine through ACH. Some people got checks. If you didn't have a bank account,
you didn't have the setup. I don't even know if you got yours, right? Basically. But like,
it's a similar thing at a much smaller scale. I'd imagine in terms of you just trying to helicopter
some funds to a specific group of people or organizations and like, how do you do that in the
existing fiat layer one system? Well, the answer is probably it's a pain in the ass.
And it's super expensive. Like, because you have to take the US file format of money,
send it through a US partner, who then converts it into whatever the local file format of money is.
Maybe it's like Argentinian pesos or Brazilian reis or whatever. That costs money. And then you
have to deposit it into the local kettle, which costs more money. And so in each case, there's
fixed fees and variable fees. And so for small sums of money, it's it literally is like not possible
to disperse these funds in an economical way, which is why they a previous to us had elected to do
these disbursements and stable funds. In the wild west of DeFi stability and innovation are
everything, which is why you should check out fracks finance, the protocol revolutionizing
stablecoins, DeFi and rollers. The core of fracks finance is a fracks USD, which is backed by black
rock institutional fiddle fund, fracks designed fracks USD for best-in-class yields across DeFi,
tea bills and carry trade returns all in one just head to fracks.com then stake it to earn some
of the best yields in DeFi want even more bridge your fracks USD over to the fracks still layer two
for the same yield plus frack still points and explore fractals diverse layer two ecosystem with
protocols like curve convex and more all rewarding early adopters. Fracks isn't just a protocol,
it's a digital nation powered by the FXS token and governed by its global community.
Acquire FXS through fracks.com or your go-to decks, stake it and help shape fracks nation's future.
Ready to join the forefront of DeFi? Visit fracks.com now to start earning with fracks USD
and staked fracks USD and for bankless listeners you can use fracks.com/r/bankless
when bridging to fracksal for exclusive fracksal perks and boosted rewards. Ethereum's layer two
universe is exploding with choices but if you're looking for the best place to park and move your
tokens make your next stop unichain. First liquidity unichain hosts the most liquid uniswap v4 deployment
on any layer two giving you deeper pools for flagship pairs like each USDC more liquidity
means better prices less slippage and smoother swaps exactly what traders crave the numbers
back it up unichain leads all layer twos in total value locked for uniswap v4 and it's not just
deep it's fast and fully transparent purpose built to be the home base for DeFi and cross-chain
liquidity when it comes to cost unichain is a no-brainer transaction fees come in about 95%
cheaper than ethereum mainnet slashing the price of creating or accessing liquidity want to stay
in the loop on unichain visit unichain.org or follow at unichain on x for all the updates let me
ask you about this just like maybe zooming out if you're you're thinking about kind of the the
layer one and being sort of the banking and almost the settlement layer for fiat for stable coins
right and the layer two is kind of this tokenized stablecoin layer with with crypto a native platform
zak if more and more starts to happen in the layer two because it's just more usable more
functional the quote unquote the fintech apps around the world and emerging economies in the US
start using that layer two more than they use the layer one what it appears to me happens is you
start to essentially bypass the existing banking settlement system at some degree or at least the
rich state the actual application happens more and more in the layer two and the banking system
just starts to become kind of a dumb settlement layer if you will they're not really doing the
kind of the cool value of creative interesting things they're not building the apps but it kind
of marginalizes the banks at some level to just doing settlement and I'm wondering about this in
the context of if that is the trajectory that we're on do you see kind of some conflict with
all of the existing traditional banks you know the JP Morgan's of the world
at Jamie Diamon I recently saw this came out and he said you know what you know there's a there's a
fintech called plaid I believe you know more about this sack but plaid taps into all of the banks
you know basically around the world and gives you a way to kind of like through their API
connected to all these banks Jamie Diamon said you know what we don't we don't want plaid
pulling customer data even on our customers behalf we're going to start throttling them
or we start charging them a fee in order to do this because we basically he's saying we don't
want to be relegated to just this dumb settlement layer with like zero percent margin compressions
essentially and so I'm wondering if more moves up into that layer two stack and it becomes more
crypto more fintech focused will the banks just like they're not going to tolerate this are they
they're going to fight back against this are are you seeing some of that I think that they
I think that some will I think that so I think that if you take if you take regulation out of the
picture completely and you just say like okay the world is this like you know government-free
libertarian paradise we would certainly move in that direction where more and more money movement
would happen through stablecoins over time you know if you kind of think of the stablecoin layer
sitting on top of the bank layer more and more deposits would aggregate to the stablecoin layer
more more consumers would solely interact through the stablecoin layer and the banking layer which
today is really big and like is the primary conduit through money movement which shrink
which shrink progressively over time and the stablecoin layer would grow over time I think
that is like the natural way things will move and and the reason is is is like purely practical
is that it's going to be easier to build applications on the stablecoin layer you're going to be able
to get better economics as a consumer or a business by building on the on that layer money is going
to move more cheaply on that layer settlements going to be more you're going to be easier on that layer
it's just going to be practical for more and more transactions to live at that layer I do think like
the big question for us over some period of time is like all money movement all finance all
financial services are downstream of regulatory requirements and so that's the big question of
like you know how much moves up to this layer and and obviously the banks are doing as much as they
can to to protect the size and importance of their of their layer i'll give you one example of that
layer so one thing it seems like the banks really want to protect is yield on essentially treasuries
yeah short duration treasuries for instance so it's part of the genius act there was this this
carve out where the bank said hey like stablecoins issuers can't directly offer that what four percent
yield directly to customers okay only banks can do this all right i'm simplifying you probably
know the complexity of it only banks can do this well it turns out in the aftermath of this
there's a little workaround that crypto is doing where you don't have the issuer like circle
give those yields to individuals who have a stablecoin at four percent you have maybe an
exchange to it and so right now i can go on coinbase for example with my usdc and i can get rewards
up to it's not quite four percent you know coinbase takes their cut whatever but i actually get
some of that yield just by holding stablecoins and you can imagine crypto and defy there could be
all sorts of different ways for people who have stablecoins to get that yield and the argument
blank slate argument would be why shouldn't they why should the banks get to keep that four percent
yield why shouldn't someone who just owns a stablecoin why shouldn't that flow back to
individuals citizens like why should this theft of four percent and this rent seeking behavior from
banks actually happened well it turns out the bank consortium is coming out and they're saying
no no no like we want to plug this loophole we don't want crypto organizations to be able to take
advantage of this yield and it seems like there's a fight between the lobbyists right now so you have
like crypto and fintech on one side versus the banks but the banks are pretty powerful they've
been in dc for a while they i don't know they control some aspect of how the game works and this
does seem like a clash of the titans in the making that's what you're saying it it does i would also
say though that it isn't necessarily crypto versus the banks because like it's not like tether is giving
that yield back yes nor nor is it like circle is giving a lot of that yield nor nor are they
incented to want to get that you'll take exactly exactly and and this is one thing i think a lot
about is that like the you know before i started bridge i kind of had this view that like things
that were um that made sense were like kind of inevitably going to happen so like um to the point
that you're making of like this this yield going back to consumers it's like it's inevitably going
to happen like you know it just makes so much sense and and so on but but but now it's like much more
clear to me that like no nothing nothing is inevitable the only things that happen are the things that
somebody or some small team of people or some large team of people fight to make happen and the
yield going back to consumers you know will really only happen if someone like us build the mechanisms
for that to happen very consistently and change the market dynamics because even if stablecoins are
successful if only us dt and us dc are the primary stablecoins in existence then you know and nobody
else issue stablecoins tethers never going to pay yield back that's just not their thing and so at
some point in time circles and coinbase are going to stop too you know and that surplus is actually
not going to go to consumers and businesses that surplus is just going to aggregate to the new
equivalent of like a visa mastercard and so you actually need folks to build you know and this
is one of the reasons why we have our stablecoin is to create mechanisms so that you know the the
benefits of stablecoins the economic rewards from stablecoins can be better diffused down to end
customers and diffuse down to end businesses which then you know improve the economics for the
platforms and so on so we think this is like really really really important there's like the
regulatory fight that's going on but there's also like just the long-term stablecoin market
structure fight that needs to the needs to happen to make sure that this creates you know surplus
for consumers it doesn't just rearrange value between you know these previous financial institutions
and these new financial institutions so being not having a dog in the race except the dog of just
like being a stablecoin holder at some level and you know representing you know just individuals
who want to receive these yields i i definitely would love to see the rent seeking you know kind
of go away and for for more of these yields return to the customer and so let's talk about maybe the
the genius bill itself and right now crypto is almost in a duopoly of stablecoins i'd say there's
tether of course with the dominant chair and then here's usdc and it appears like these like liquidity
of begets liquidity and it does appear to be that there's kind of power law dominance at play here
that said we're only at what like 270 billion or so okay and stablecoins are going to grow well
into the trillions and the genius bill opens the door for all sorts of new issuers to enter the
market we already have some fintechs playing the game there's the paypal stablecoin they've entered
you guys have your own i imagine stripe is going to do something big here there's also talk of you
know amazon could enter the ring walmart could enter the ring and so it does seem like post genius
we're going to be in this a period of time where we're going to see all sorts of different issuers
enter and all sorts of different experiments at play all trying to get as much liquidity as they can
and get a dominant position and all will have different takes on it so how do you think this
stablecoin market will now play out post genius maybe you can talk about like stripe what what you
guys are thinking there but then also just like generally do you see a whole bunch of experiments
that will play out or like what is the structure here our view is that there will be many many
different stablecoins i think that every platform should have its own stablecoin i think that you
know we're we could see a world where there are tens or hundreds or hundreds of thousands or
millions of different stablecoins however the differences between these stablecoins will be like
totally abstracted away and so i think you're only going to have a handful of like branded
stablecoins that people know and name you know the usdt usdcs and and i think usdt and usdcs are
going to be way more successful tomorrow than they are today and like we obviously hope that they are
because they're doing like an enormous service to the space and and there are real network
effects to their businesses they're building liquidity they're they're they're building FX
trading pairs you know this is like very hard for you know paypal tried and spent a ton of money
to break in and build liquidity for py usd and it's been hard it's a very you know there's probably
room for five or some handful of these branded stablecoins and then i think that platforms
when platforms are building with stablecoins you know like robin hood is building with stablecoins
or you know a amazon you mentioned or walmart or you know banks are building with stablecoins
they're going to choose to have those stablecoins be stablecoins that they control and the reason
is that they're primarily going to be internal stablecoins that they're going to be using to move
money amongst their users to disperse funds to their customers those liquidity benefits the usdcs
you have are irrelevant for their internal use case like walmart moving money between it's like
20 different entities or whatever across europe is just internal transfers they're going to
want it to be in their own stablecoin they're going to want it because they want to control
the reserves they don't want them to be you know how that you know with circle and commingled with
everyone else they're going to want direct access to the to the yield and they're going to want to
control the the dollar that it is you know like right now some of these issuers are charging burn
fees to get out of the money like why would you ever move a bunch of your internal funds into
a stablecoin that charged you money to to convert back out up it makes it worse than fiat funds so
you know you're going to want to control your own money it is like like like not not in like a
decentralized way of it but like you don't want to be beholden to some other platform
whose interests will be supreme to your own if you if money movement is poor to your business
in some way a shape or form okay fasting so let me make sure I understand like you're like the
world that you're describing your world so you see a world of maybe say it call it a handful
of branded external stablecoins the types that we see in a tether or usdc and each of those I
got to imagine it's going to have its own stick its own thing right it's like right now tether is
kind of used mostly outside of the us and the rest of the world international world kind of prefers
it usdc is known as kind of the compliant coin maybe there's room for another maybe there's room
for one that kind of uh provides a way to pass yield back to its customers or there's some other
things that might be but these are a small set of external kind of stablecoin players but then
every major company is going to have their own internal corporate stablecoin as well and I almost
think of like you think about starbucks gift card points right now and they sort of have that in
a way it's not in a fungible erc 20 stablecoin type of setup but it exists inside of the starbucks
balance sheet so you see a world of that and then you see a world of many thousands of these things
hundreds of thousands many millions of these things but I got to imagine they are all
composable with each other right like I don't want to have my wells Fargo dollars and they're no good
at you know JP Morgan because the JP Morgan has JP Morgan dollars and I got to do a swap here
that all has to work the way it works today which is all be kind of fungible anyway just like is
that the world that you're you're thinking can it disabuse me of some of these things if you will
yeah I mean I mean totally and two really quick examples so let's say that every bank is moving
funds with stablecoins because of settlement benefits or what have you wells Fargo is never
going to use JP Morgan stablecoin it's just never never going to happen only to wells Fargo yeah never
because because all of JP Morgan's you know stablecoins have reserves held at JP Morgan so that would
mean that that wells Fargo's reserves are now held at JP Morgan it just makes no sense so that's like
never never gonna have it okay the another example is like let's say your polymarket so polymarket
today operates primarily with stablecoins you're gonna enable just like polymarket does today
for people to bet with whatever stablecoin they want they could send in USDT they could send in
USDC they could eventually they'll be able to send in dollars they can send in whatever and then
internal to polymarket you're gonna want this to run on poly USD or some stablecoin that is
internal to polymarket because you're gonna want to make sure that if polymarket ever builds their
own layer two that their stablecoin could go to that layer two you don't have to convince some
issuer somewhere else to move the stablecoin over and make it work you're gonna want to make
sure that there are never burn fees tied to this so that you can always you know handle
redemptions without any cost you're eventually gonna want to program some aspect of the smart
contract of these dollars yourself and so it's going to be important for polymarket to control the
dollar that it the programmatic and tokenized dollar that it builds on so that they can control
their future they probably also want to share the yield right if your polymarket yes yes yes
exactly exactly so we we think this is the world that that should exist but but it's one of those
things like it has to be built and so the genius act is like a very important first step to enabling
it to be built and enabling much more receptivity to it and then there's a bunch of work that we
need to do actually make it happen but back to your example so let's say Wells Fargo pushes money
to JP Morgan what do they use it like what's kind of do they have to go to an in-between
stablecoin do they have to go to USDC or something in order to get it to JP Morgan or do they handle
that you know in the back end back to the kind of the layer one the fiat system again yeah what
what I imagine will happen is there will be a whole like clearing house for stablecoins okay and so
every day these these stablecoins will move between banks and then the end of the day reserves will
only will net and move like the actual layer one settlement will be cleaned up and balanced
at the end of every day and so you'll only end up moving the net amount which is roughly similar
ish to how things kind of work today with kind of different settlement windows but I think that's
how it will it will work one really cool thing about maybe what you're doing at Stripe is it appears
to me it's just in this area where FinTechs are all going through their crypto transformation
it seems like Stripe is now signed up to fully go and be one of the pioneers of going through
their crypto transformation so it's interesting I've been tracking the the calls in brothers for a
while and they tried some things in crypto previously right including Bitcoin in the past they were
skeptical of that it seems like now this is the first and they I think they tried to degrade in
the lightning network and you know like all of these things early just crypto experiments this is
the first time we've seen Stripe go all in on something in crypto and it started with stablecoins
the acquisition of bridge and now they've also purchased privy which is sort of a crypto wallet
infrastructure type company so they're making some big plays here but it's just a macro meta of of
you know FinTech companies going through a crypto transformation I'm wondering if we could
project maybe use your mind you're kind of seeing the futures you saw stablecoin very early
five years later or so and what what does FinTech look like five years later after we've gone through
this convergence period you know something like Venmo is something maybe our American listeners
use every day does that turn into like a crypto wallet are we using rather than you know the the
dollars inside of PayPal are they is the backing of those or are they actually all stablecoins
underneath like what sort of things do you think we'll we'll see happen through this convergence if
we project five years later I think that most financial assets will be tokenized and as a result
I think the foundational building block for every FinTech will be a wallet wow and I think that it's
like you know today people think of it as like this whole new world that they have to go and
like learn about and participate in and so on and it's just going to be you're going to hit an
API like a bridge and you're going to create an account for a user and that account is just
going to be a wallet and you're going to in that account you're going to enable us currency which
will just be a stablecoin and then you'll enable euro currency which will be a different stablecoin
and then you'll enable you know reis which will just be a different stablecoin and then you'll
enable stock trading which will just be you know another tokenized form of stocks and so on and
and I think that we're sort of like you know barring any regulatory dramatic regulatory changes we're
sort of on this glide path today and and one of the things I think that's like the like that is
kind of the most interesting dynamic that will play out to me is you kind of have
all these crypto wallets that started you know obviously in the crypto space that are over time
going to move more into the you know traditional financial financial services realm and then you
have all these more tradfi companies that are moving into crypto direction yeah and
you know over time they will become blended but like take Robinhood as an example you know Robinhood
obviously started very traditional with stock trading and so on they've moved pretty heavily
into into crypto trading and now one of their big bets is to go international and so how do you go
international as a as a fintech you know the the way that I think they're choosing to do it I don't
have any insider info on them but like one of the ways if I were them I would do it is you build a
wallet core to core to Robinhood and then the amazing thing about a blockchain is it's like is
it's like you know open sourced financial services and so then you're building on top of let's say
Solana or some some blockchain any time any developer anywhere in the world adds something
you know to Solana that is now accessible to Robinhood it's a little bit old it's open 24 hours a day
it's accessible in every country with an internet connection it is the old way of building financial
services is you had to build everything yourself as a company you know if someone wanted to replicate
revenue they have to build all the you know they have to build the regulated infrastructure and
in the next country and the next car product and the next stock they have to build it all
themselves the amazing thing about blockchain is that people build a tokenized BRL for Solana
and now boom Robinhood doesn't have to add that but now Robinhood has you know Brazilian REI
deposits natively and now you can store a balance in BRL in Robinhood easily and someone else
build that and then someone else builds euros and now they can now they can store euros and then
someone else builds tokenized treasuries and now they can offer treasury yields and so you you actually
open source your financial stack and let the world build and then you internalize those services
and and this is why I think that everything will move will move on chain because you move from
this world of like individual companies building up which are limited by their own capacity to a
world where you have this massive shared resource of everything that's built on a blockchain and
you're just internalizing those services it's funny because it's a simple narrative but we've
we've said this is the way it's playing out and now it seems like you're you're saying that it's
actually playing up this way which is basically all of the the bank accounts that we use they
become crypto wallets in the future whether we know it or not you know it could be on the back end
but they all become crypto wallets and all of the assets that we hold they become tokens they're
crypto tokens somewhere one other question I guess with this is we've seen some fintechs like
Robinhood for example and even Coinbase I guess maybe Coinbase is now more of like moving toward
the fintech company they they also launched their own ledgers so those two have layer twos of course
and then we've seen some companies you know circle notably recently launching a layer one
they're having kind of a stable coins maybe a payments layer one there's also been news recently
that stripe is going down the path of launching its own layer one in fact there was an announcement
recently that of the tempo project and some detail of what you guys are doing there how does that
fit into the stack do all of the banks they're effectively I guess private ledgers on the scenes
anyway do all of them convert to become sort of private slash public ledgers blockchain ledgers
essentially and launch their own layer ones or layer twos how do you see that evolve well for us
it has evolved very naturally I mean we I would say bridge was probably one of the first I don't
know if we were the first but we certainly felt like one of the first companies to try to build
payment scale infrastructure on a blockchain and it was really hard like and continues to be
really hard blockchains are good for a lot of things but they are not great at payment scale
functionality like like building something on a theorem I could imagine just you have gas fees
even Solana take take the blockchain that everybody loves and thinks is like the poster child for
TPS and so on so so we had a customer come to us the other day they have millions of accounts
they want to enable stablecoin accounts for all of their customers in order to do that you have to
spin up a Solana wallet for everyone and you have to prime that wallet to accept us DC both of those
things require soul and about 30 cents of soul in order to do that so it was going to cost them
hundreds of thousands if not millions of dollars just to enable this product because that is the way
this lana blockchain is as designed it was just not designed with this type of use case of like
some developer coming along with millions of accounts and wanting to enable it like no one
is going not no one but very few people are going to just like spend you know a million dollars just
to enable functionality that your users haven't even tested yet or there's you know very early on
with the deliverability of you know these aid programs we had to send thousands of payments
out at the same time with fiat infrastructure you know fiat moves super slowly it moves so slowly
in fact that we have built insane amounts of infrastructure on top of it to make sure that money
does not move and so and so with fiat infrastructure what ends up happening is let's say you wanted
you wanted to you know pay tens of thousands of people all at the same time you know you would
use something like PayPal you know and you would load all the money into PayPal and then you click
a button and then it would just be ledger updates to update people's accounts so the money wouldn't
actually move you'd load it in like three days before make sure it settles and so on but with a
blockchain that's that's not how it happens everybody has their own wallet so you actually
have to move the money into people's individual wallets and sending 20,000 30,000 50,000 transactions
on a blockchain at the exact same time is not possible no matter what blockchain you you try to
you try to send it on and so the first time we did this aid disbursement on stellar we were super naive
we were like okay click button send money and it took like 18 hours for us to process through
all of these transactions on stellar which is another pretty high throughput blockchain
and a huge percentage of them failed and were picked up and then there were all these support
requests that came in because people were like hey you said my money would be delivered at like
9 a.m. but it's still not here and so on and so then we had to build all this infrastructure to
simulate to like make it such that you know we prioritize different transactions and we could like
minimize the number of support requests like a like a quick example is that like we took
every transaction that was over like 50 dollars which was like a big payout and we prioritize those
first because those are the people who are going to check and then we like set up you know seven
or eight different like synchronous jobs to send out these payments and then we progressively would
move down there was no way to deliver them all in real time anyways blockchains are just struggle
with with payment scale problems and so the way we came into this is that we needed to build the
infrastructure that solved our unique pay points we weren't focused on when we still aren't focused
on trading we just want something that's super high throughput that has like some core functionality
that's important for payments payments companies and and and has the deliverability that everyone
is looking for if they're going to run their bank if they're going to run if they're going to pay
all their customers if they're going to run payroll on top of this rail and so for us building and
investing in tempo became super important but but just to be very clear about tempo tempo is not
like a strike blockchain we we also did not believe that these like private corporate blockchains would
be successful because people aren't going to want to build on someone else's blockchain they want
to build on like shared infrastructure that they believe is going to be good for everyone it's the
same reason that the same skepticism we have about everyone building on someone else's stablecoin
right you don't want to subordinate your interests to those of some other you know uh
economically interested party and so that's why tempo is actually a a stripe is a major contributor
it's a tempo bridges a major contributor and collaborator on tempo but tempo is an independent
entity you know and a neutral blockchain um built outside of strep so tempo is going to be an
independent entity a neutral blockchain that is also a layer one EVM type of uh is that that
layer one layer one EVM super focused on TPS no noisy neighbor problems you know your your
transactions are not going to get stuck because like Trump coin came out which happened to us on
Solana you know there's going to be private transactions which are super important to every
payments payments company there will be very quick finality uh which is also really important
you know Ethereum it's like 12 minutes to get financial like sub one second finality so a bunch
of stuff that's very very important to pay and it would allow you guys to do a use case like if
you had a million people let's say in the US and you wanted to just send them each uh a stimulus
check for instance um yeah you could just do that on this chain basically they could pick it up and
they could pick it up in their base you know any EVM compatible wallet that they used and boom it
would be there right basically you know it has the scale to do that yeah and importantly we could
do it or PayPal could use it and do it if it was helpful for PayPal you know this is like this is
where it is we view this as like a very important public good for the broader stablecoin ecosystem
and so you know Stripe is a major contributor to it we are investing and building on top of uh
on top of tempo but we will have the same rights and interests you know uh to roadmap or whatever
is anybody else so how do you think Zac this will evolve like specifically layer ones you know
fintechs like Stripe getting kind of the layer one business we've seen Circle get into kind of the
the layer one business it is the case definitely that within crypto and generally you know the
advent of more centralized stablecoins has not taken away from the crypto native assets that we have
like something like Bitcoin or Ethereum or Ether you know um actually it's kind of accelerated the
growth of some of these core assets and so they're kind of growing in parallel they're not they don't
settle down to kind of the as you call it the layer one of fiat at all they have this whole
independent settlement network and they've grown alongside stablecoins what do you see
happening with layer ones there are some people out there and i'm specifically talking about maybe
a Stripe layer one uh like a tempo and again you're saying it's not a Stripe layer one but something
like type that something like tempo right do these eat the market share away from some of our public
blockchains the ethereum's of the world and the layer two's and the slaunas of the world do they
complement them how do these interact and how do you see this evolving will every fintech will
every bank uh you know polish its own layer one or maybe kind of a layer two or will there be some
power law winners to that game how do you see the ledger piece of all i i think that you know with
tempo it's very complimentary our view is that like we the reason why tempo needs to exist is
because the functionality that it is providing does not exist in the market and so the the stable
corn space itself would be much smaller without something like a tempo and in existence because
you just do not have the infrastructure on top of which someone can build payment scale operations
today it like just doesn't doesn't exist and it's not even close um and and so in that respect i
view it as extremely complimentary to uh all of the other you know blockchains that exists today i
do think that um my mental model is that you will have a few kind of like general purpose blockchains
that exists you know and i think like base is a great example like base is like clearly gonna be
a winner it's a great sir great great product that the coinbase team has created um it's a general
purpose blockchain and you know salana is another one there will be a few of these i think it's very
hard for someone now to create like uh i'm just going to create a generic blockchain and hope
that it attracts a lot of volume now i think we're entering a phase where folks are going to build
blockchains that solve very specific problems that these general purpose blockchains don't solve
this is what we're doing with payments use cases i've talked to other teams who are building block
chains for trading use cases like very very very high throughput low latency trading use cases
which requires a totally different set of requirements and and these blockchains will solve like very
specialized things that the generic blockchains will not will not solve and and then i think there
will be a third type of blockchain which will be like um maybe like coming back to the polymarket
polymarket might build its own blockchain so that it controls its own block space and so on these
will be application specific blockchains and so you'll move in like there'll be a few very general
then a few sort of like feature specific blockchains which is where we're going with tempo and then
there will be many application specific blockchains that's my mental model today very much subject
to change a whole bunch of blockchains so i use a whole bunch of movement on chain and so
five years from now where does this like position fintech or just find how finance works maybe in
the u.s and around the world so if you kind of go down enough layers i think traditional finance
in the banking system and back to kind of the settlement layer of that layer one i don't know
it's all like ibm main mainframes written in like cobalt it's like some nasty weird stuff and a whole
bunch of paperwork if you do anything in finance it's still i appears digital on the surface layer
but like i think there's offices of like people doing paperwork in the background you know not
faxing things around but like that is that the legal documents are all just like still paper and
i can't believe this so and they might actually be faxing yeah exactly and so are we basically
doing a um i don't know a a switch from that existing legacy system and just like migrating
more and more to these new krypto krypto blockchain based systems and doing that over time and so
basically what happens is the fintech user interface stops using the mainframe tradfi
back end and starts settling more and more into blockchain yeah i mean i think that's what's
going to i think that's what's going to happen and and i think that you know today to to like
take a bridge specific example you know our business was built our very first product the
product that that kind of like made our business was stablecoin orchestration which was moving
money between fiat and stablecoin this layer one and this layer two and doing it a lot because
people needed to do it a lot you know and still today need to do it a lot what i think will happen
for our business is that will become an increasingly niche service um over time that's what i hope
happens is that you increasingly need to settle to the layer one and like you know take the the
bank example that i went through before you're gonna have you know millions of different stablecoin
movements for every one fiat movement whereas today it's kind of like one for one
um you know or even even two fiat movements for every one stablecoin movement um and and
i hope that ratio changes over time and i think that's what success is is more and more of the
financial services that we have today can be facilitated and settled on this blockchain layer
and uh but but we're still like it's like hard to even begin to express how early we are
in this in this journey just coming back to it like the basic things of like sending a bunch
of transactions simultaneously are really hard to do like really really really hard to do
on uh on a stablecoin we don't have any local stablecoins you know the stablecoin market is like
99.9 percent us dollars yeah which is great which is great for the first use case of stablecoins
which is like trading and like access to us dollars but if you want this to become a core part of
the financial system you need local stablecoins like i'm very optimistic that those will be very
important in the next like five to ten years so there's just a bunch of pretty big building blocks
that we don't have today so the secretary of treasury says by 2028 he's citing other research
that will have you know three trillion or so in stablecoins on chain i mean do you do you agree
is that the kind of scale we're going to grow to i mean how quickly and how fast does this grow
and how how large does it become i mean i think that's us stablecoins so i i think that there it
could be orders like an order of magnitude bigger or you know if you if we're successful at bringing
on you know tokenize euros and tokenize pesos and tokenize yen and and so on but that is also
downstream of regulation so today you know one of the great things is like the us is kind of
you know very quickly went from a laggard to a leader in in sort of regulatory clarity which
helps us sort of speedrun a bunch of these markets but we need the same thing all around the world
so what is holding us back at this point from basically the entire world all of finance um
adopting crypto and making that switch even sooner i mean you mentioned regulatory and so maybe
that would be in your top three list there's also i mean ux still is kind of hard in crypto i mean
we still have wallets with seed phrases uh in in many cases that are sort of difficult um there's
also you know do we have the chargeback protection consumer protections that something like visa or
the established credit card companies have do we even have on i guess the compliance and privacy side
you know amlkyc that would be necessary for countries to adopt this uh like what are the top
three things missing do you think still in the stack for for crypto to get to the trillions and go
completely mainstream in the way that you've been describing i think the um the the most straightforward
answer is like you know regulatory clarity and accounting clarity that's that's probably the
most straightforward answer but but i would say more tangibly for us what i have felt is the biggest
barrier is education so stablecoin we've had decades where teams and uh have built expertise
and familiarity of building on top of fiat systems and so you go into any company that
moves money and there are dozens of people who understand how to do fbo accounts and build internal
ledgers and maybe even send you know ach batch files and like all this crazy stuff but people
have built those skills over many many many years and then you go in and you talk to them about
spinning up a wallet and everyone's like head explodes you know you would think that you're
asking them to go to mars or something it's like a totally new financial stack that's completely
unfamiliar and so the biggest thing that we face is this like this lack of familiarity with this
new platform like it's a new technology it's a new platform and it touches the thing that is like
the lifeblood of every company and and so people are very risk-averse and i i would say that's like
you know we'd probably be moving like a hundred x-faster if we had one person in every single
company who is deeply familiar with crypto the the other thing is that there just are not very
many engineers on the planet that understand crypto the number of folks who understand smart
contracts the number of folks who've built with wallets it's probably one of the smallest
engineering communities in the world like if you're an engineer and you're looking for you know
where do you position yourself to have like the most unique skill set imaginable it is like
very obviously in the crypto space like super obviously in the crypto space uh it's something
that's going to be phenomenally important to the world it's something that's going to touch
money movement at every company you know on every continent and there are you know only you know
hundreds of people it feels like in the world you know this space really really well there are
a lot of engineers that stripe of course and now you're part of a bigger engineering team let's say
and uh so for Patrick and John you know we talked a little bit about their um yeah experience in
crypto and kind of moving to a more bullish stance how crypto peeled are they at this point how crypto
peeled is stripe so when when i when we were like going through the acquisition process i went to
the stripe offices to have launch with um john and and patrick and i like walked in and i think this
maybe was like the first time i met john in person and um the first thing he he said to me he was like
so can i tell you a joke and i was like yeah sure he's like he's like what's the difference
between a bank and tether and i was like i don't know and he was like well one of them is like this
big institution that holds a ton of money and you have no idea where the money is and if you ever
want to get your money out you may not be able to because it's in all these super esoteric
assets and there's literally no visibility into where the money is held and the other one is a
stable coin i mean he has a point and so uh i i think that like at a at a pretty deep level
they are um very you know big believers in like the stable coin space and like very much
understand the promise of the technology i mean they were they were believers in stellar you know
i think stripe was one of the original investors in stellar way back when they obviously experimented
with bitcoin realized that wasn't going to work super well for payments for a bunch of reasons
um and uh and and so i think when they like you know as stable coin start having this moment and
they sort of learn more about bridge in the use case that we were selling pieces clicked into place
stripe is an absolutely massive company um with tons of uh relationships so what's your hope for
how crypto kind of saturates uh stripe and you know how this fintech company converges into uh uh
fintech company going through a a crypto transformation uh i mean i think one of the things that i am
the most excited about is um you know with the products that we build i kind of am like like i
don't think anybody is going to want to use a stable coin just to use a stable coin people are
going to want to use a stable coin or build with wallets or use our apis because we deliver some
very tangible business value to them we enable them to enter a new country we enable them to serve
more consumers we enable them to save money we enable them to generate revenue but there needs
to be some very tangible benefit that we provide and one of the really nice things now about being
part of stripe is that the feedback loop on understanding that tangible value is like
you know the minimus because now we have a first best customer for everything that we want to do
and so you know it's not like stripe is you know stripe is eight thousand people so even if like
john or patrick or whomever are like hey we want to build with stable coins there needs to be you
know dozens of people who deeply understand the benefit to actually work on the thing and do it
and so if we encounter pushback from those teams of stripe it's the same pushback that we would
encounter if we were like talking to walmart or talking to robin hood or talking to um
revolute or new bank or whomever uh and so it gives us an opportunity now to like as we push
stripe you know stable coins deeper into stripe to understand where concerns are
figure out how to overcome those concerns and turn stripe into like our first best customer
and then it becomes like a great proof point for all these folks externally guess you're full
circle back to zulu all over again right yeah exactly exactly uh as we close the sad zak uh
we've been talking about stable coin users as if they're all human there is another future where
the biggest stable coin users out there the the actual unbanked uh could be ais and ai agents um
what are you guys going to do with stripe to uh play a role in that transformation you think ais
will be huge stable coin users and if so how far away uh are we from that future i was um
so simon taylor shared this thing with me the other the other day forget like maybe was on slack
or something but he said that he was talking to this like money historian and every single time
there's been some new technological revolution there has been a new form of money that helps
facilitate the progress of this revolution and a great example of this that we can all relate to
is credit cards and the internet uh you know the internet wouldn't be what it is without credit
cards and obviously credit cards wouldn't be what they are without the internet um you know credit
cards were around a long time before the internet like you know in the 60s uh but they really took
off credit and debit cards and so on in the late 90s into the into the 2000s and now you
could not imagine the internet without without credit cards it's like the default way value is
transferred and obviously stripe is a big accelerant of this of this trip and i think stable coins
are going to be the same thing for ai i think a new form of money is going to be required to
facilitate you know uh economic activity between all these agents you know the existing fiat system
has some like challenges for ai you know one of the most obvious of which is that in order to
store fiat money you need to be a human yeah that's kind of a problem if you're not
that's a that's a real problem and and so what i think will happen is that we'll go through this
challenge progressively like you know at first a lot of ai agents will be tethered to humans
so they will piggyback off of human kyc and so on um but over time they will need their own accounts
their own be able to make their own decisions and you know stable coins and wallets make that
possible the the other thing is that is that stable coins and wallets end up uh are really good for
small transactions for variable transactions for streaming transactions um and so they make a lot
of different types of money movement possible that are not that are not really possible today when
you actually have to move money across this layer one that's super expensive and super slow yeah
it's incredible it does seem super obvious to me that the um the finance stack the banking stack
that ai will use will be crypto how could it not be wallets and and ledgers and and smart contracts
and actual tokens that they can hold uh that's got to be the future so maybe the next um move for
you guys zak is to build the bridge between kind of the the ai layer and uh and the rest of crypto
um this has been fantastic thank you so much for joining us today zak i know stripes got some big
announcements uh to come in the future and and we appreciate you hanging out with us today thanks
for having me on it's been fun gotta let you know of course bankless listener none of this has been
financial advice crypto is risky you could lose what you put in but we are headed west this is the
frontier it's not for everyone but we're glad you're with us on bankless journey thanks a lot